Wu Yue

Mobile phone: (+86) 18521091920 Email: yuewu51@outlook.com

Project & product manager with 6+ years' experience in business strategy and analytics related product and project management through leading cross-functional/geolocational/cultural teams, with solid knowledge in business and financial analyses. Demonstrated fast-learning and adaptiveness by solid track records in multiple roles throughout the career.



Experience

Alibaba Group - Cloud & Technology	Hangzhou	2021/6-now (12 months)
Cloud Product Release Manager	Hybrid Cloud	2021/6-now (12 months)

- Responsible for ensuring timely and quality development and delivery of hybrid cloud solutions (Apsara Stack) through coordinating cross-functional teams.
- Responsible for cloud solution development efficiency and ROI enhancement and risk mitigation through (re-)designing development process, defining and operating key KPIs through coordinating toolchain and data warehouse teams.

General Electric China R&D Center	Shanghai	2015/11 – 2020/7 (4 years 9 months)
Project & Product Manager	Aviation Digital	2018/9 - 2020/7 (22 months)

- Responsible for full life cycle management of machine learning and analytics projects for airline customers, covering reliability, supply chain, and maintenance businesses using statistics, computer vision, natural language processing, and reinforcement learning technologies. Managed up to 7 concurrent projects involving 20+ people with 100% first time yield and over 85% on time delivery.
- Responsible for designing digital product portfolio strategy for internal & external customer's reliability
 and supply chain businesses that enables data governance, insight extraction, and decision making for
 improved operations productivity.

Product Manager / Sr. Data Scientist Aviation Digital 2016/12 – 2018/8 (21 months)

- As Product Manager, responsible for full life cycle management of a machine learning modeling tool for aircraft and marine engine predictive maintenance for all GE Aviation engine analytics engineers.
- As Data Scientist, responsible for analytics and machine learning modeling for engine maintenance and service cost-out

Mechanical Engineer Aviation Engineering 2015/11 – 2016/11 (13 months)

• Responsible for supporting mechanical analysis of engine. Led a project that improved productivity of certain analytics task by 3x, netting \$167K/year worth benefit. The project won the Young Engineer Award on 2017 GE Aviation Engineering Recognition Day.

Projects

Strategy Design of a Digital Product Portfolio for Airlines Reliability Business 2020/3 – 2020/7

This project designed a digital product portfolio that connected existing seed analytics products with missing pieces to form line and surfaces that aimed to completely cover airlines reliability business.

- Managed seed products development projects to understand underlying machine learning technologies;
- Independently conducted market research, combined with customer engagement to understand the business and its pain points;
- Designed closed loop product portfolio according to the business value chain, data chain, and identified
 pain points that used digital and machine learning technologies to add value in each phase through
 improving data governance, insight extraction, and decision making;
- Designed product portfolio roadmap, business model, and customer onboarding plan.

The portfolio strategy was highly recognized by engineering and commercial directors of China Aviation Digital business as a reference for future portfolio development and business development.

Digital Consulting Service for a Domestic Aircraft Manufacturer

2018/11 – 2019/12

This project delivered an architecture design of a digital platform to provide data governance, analytics development, and analytics servicing for this customer and its airlines customers, plus proof-of-concept analytics applications based on customer data.

- Acted as project manager responsible for overall execution and inter-team communication involving 20+ people from 5 internal functional teams and 5 customer departments;
- Led discovery workshop at customer site to collect and analyze customer needs;

- Developed two POC analytics using statistic and classic machine learning methods to demonstrate the platform's potential business application in flight safety and predictive maintenance;
- Led conceptual design of the clickable visual demo that hosted all prospective analytics applications, and worked with UED lead to finish the details;
- Delivered Python-based analytics development trainings at customer site to improve customer's digital awareness and recognition in GE.

Project deliverables were highly recognized by customer, strengthening the strategic partnership as a new milestone and earning preference for pipeline projects for GE.

Digital Consulting Service for A Premier Airline in Greater China Region

2018/4 - 2018/8

As the first digital consulting service for this customer, this project aimed to improve customer's digital awareness and develop digital products and services sales opportunities.

- As the only on-site consultant and responsible for project execution. Reported directly to GE Aviation global VP during project execution;
- Identified 22 potential digital empowering opportunities including lean process, data governance, visualization, and analytics to help improve customer's aircraft operations efficiency through interviews and workshops with 8 customer teams within two weeks;
- Developed an aircraft component analytics model by leading a 10+ people global mission-based team. The
 model had 95% precision and estimated \$0.8M annual loss reduction from flight delays and cancellations
 through accurate data-driven fault diagnosis and prediction.

This project built excellent reputation and customer relation for GE Aviation digital business and catalyzed GE's first digital product sale deal with this customer.

Digital Product for Automatic Engine Predictive Maintenance Modeling

2017/1 - 2019/4

This project designed, developed, and delivered a prototype analytics platform product for engine predictive maintenance by consolidating modeling methodology into standardized application (Jupyter-based) backed by open source machine learning packages (sklearn) and its customized extension to achieve centralized, standardized, and trackable management of model development, and modular and continuous modeling process evolution.

- As product manager, initiated and owned full life cycle management of the product by leading 3 global teams:
- First time adoption of GitHub and CICD for large scale analytics product in GE Aviation, overcoming multiple organizational, procedural, and cultural obstacles.

This product was integrated into GE's generic analytics develop platform (Dataiku) and became the standard model development tool for engine predictive maintenance, helping global analytics teams reduce development time from 6 months to 1~2 months per model and improve model performance potential from modern feature engineering and selection methods. The project was nominated for The G. R. I. T. (Guts, Resilience, Initiative, Tenacity) Award for 2019 GE Digital Recognition Day.

Education

2010/9–2015/7 University of Michigan – Shanghai Jiao Tong University Joint Institute M.S. in Mechanical Engineering¹

2006/9–2010/7 University of Michigan – Shanghai Jiao Tong University Joint Institute B.S. in Mechanical engineering, Outstanding Graduate

Trainings & Certifications

- Alibaba Cloud ACP certification
- PMP (training only, not certificated)

CFA level I passed

Skills

Mandarin: Native

- English: Business Fluent
- MS Office: Proficient
- Machine learning: familiar with sklearn-based classic algorithms; familiar with principles of deep learning and reinforcement learning
- Python: Proficient
- R: Familiar

SQL: Proficient

¹ Awarded by a 5-year PhD program, which was partially finished due to personal reason.

吴越

移动电话: (+86) 18521091920 电子邮箱: yuewu51@outlook.com

拥有超过6年战略和分析相关的产品和项目管理经验。善于大型企业中跨职能/地域/文化团队合作。拥有坚实的商业和财务分析基础。善于快速学习、拥抱变化。

工作经历



- 协同混合云、各云产品和交付运维团队,保障混合云解决方案(Apsara Stack)的版本按时保质完成研发和交付。
- 通过流程改进与设计与运营 KPI,协同工具链和数仓团队,帮助云解决方案研发提升效率和 ROI,降低风险。

通用电气中国研发中心	上海	2015/11 - 2020/7(4年9个月)
项目经理/产品经理	航空数字化部	2019/12 - 2020/7(8 个月)

- 负责机器学习和数据分析项目的全生命周期管理,内容覆盖航空公司的可靠性、供应链和维护业务,涉及统计学、计算机视觉、自然语言处理及强化学习技术。最多同时管理 7 个项目,涉及 20 余人,达成 100%首次交付成功率和大于 85%按时交付率。
- 负责制定面向内外部客户可靠性和供应链业务的的数字化产品集的发展战略,帮助客户通过数据 治理、洞察提取和智能决策提升运营效率。

产品经理/高级数据科学家 航空数字化部 2016/12 - 2019/11 (21 个月)

- 作为产品经理,负责面向通用电气航空全球发动机分析工程师的发动机预测性维护建模工具的全生命周期管理。
- 作为数据科学家,负责发动机维护及其降成本相关的分析和机器学习建模。

■ 支持发动机力学分析。领导了一个生产力提升项目,通过改进已有的高性能计算服务器的使用流程和工具,帮助团队在 1 个月内完成原计划 3 个月完成的分析任务,按时保质交付某大客户的关键项目,并实现了每年价值 16.7 万美元的效用。该项目获得了通用电气航空业务集团 2017 年度工程表彰日青年工程师奖。

项目经历

航空公司可靠性业务数字化产品集战略设计

2020/3-2020/7

本项目将若干种子产品和潜在的产品机会由点到线到面地结合起来,设计了一个数字化产品集,以全面覆盖航空公司的可靠性业务。

- 管理种子产品开发项目以了解底层的机器学习技术;
- 独立完成市场调研,结合客户访谈,了解业务和痛点;
- 依据业务的价值链、数据链和总结出的痛点设计了闭环产品集,运用数字化和机器学习技术改善数据治理、洞见提取和智能决策,在每个环节创造价值;
- 设计产品集的路线图、商业模式和客户引导方案。

该产品集战略被中国航空数字化业务的工程和商务总监高度认可,为未来该产品集的工程开发和业务发展提供了重要参考。

为国内某飞机制造商提供数字化咨询服务

2018/11-2019/12

该项目交付了航空大数据平台的架构设计,通过提供数据治理、分析模型开发和分析服务,支持客户及其中小航空公司客户的数字化运营。项目同时交付了2个基于客户数据的概念验证分析模型。

- 作为项目经理,负责项目整体执行和协调 5 个内部职能团队和 5 个客户部门之间的沟通;
- 领导在客户现场开展发现工作坊(discovery workshop),收集和分析客户需求;

- 运用统计学和经典机器学习方法开发了 2 个概念验证分析模型,分别展示了大数据平台在飞行安全和预测性维护上的应用前景;
- 负责平台的分析服务前端的互动可视化演示文档(clickable visual demo)的概念设计,并与 UED 团队合作完成细节设计;
- 在客户现场开展了基于 Python 的分析建模培训,帮助客户提高了数字化意识和对公司团队的认可度。

该项目通用电气与该客户在航空数字化领域战略合作的重要里程碑,获得了客户的高度认可,为通用电气赢得了后续项目意向。

为大中华区某高端航空公司提供航空数字化咨询服务

2018/4 - 2018/8

该项目作为为该客户提供的首个数字化咨询服务,旨在提高客户的数字化意识、发掘数字化产品和服务的销售机会。

- 作为唯一的现场咨询师负责项目的执行,项目期间直接向通用电气航空全球副总裁汇报;
- 在2周内与8个客户团队开展多次访谈和工作坊,找出了22个数字化赋能机会,涵盖精益流程、数据治理、可视化和分析建模等类型,帮助客户提升运营效率;
- 领导10余人的临时全球团队开发了1个飞机关键部件维护模型,准确率达95%,通过数据驱动的故障诊断和预警,预计能帮助客户每年避免8万美元由航班延误和取消造成的损失。

该项目获得了客户的高度认可,促成了通用电气航空对该客户的首个数字产品的订单。

发动机预测性维护自动建模中台产品

2017/1 - 2019/4

该项目设计、开发和交付了一个分析中台原型,以开源机器学习算法包(sklearn)和自主开发的拓展包为基础,将通用电气发动机预测性维护的建模方法论固化到标准应用中(基于 Jupyter),实现了对模型开发的集中化、标准化和可追溯管理,以及模块化、持续化的建模流程改进。

- 作为项目发起人和产品经理,负责产品的全生命周期管理,领导3个全球团队完成产品开发;
- 首次在通用电气航空业务集团内采用 GitHub 和 CICD 的方式开发和部署大型分析产品,期间克服了来自自组织结构、流程和文化方面的多重阻力。

该产品成为了公司内发动机预测性建模的标准工具,最终被部署在通用电气的通用数据分析云平台上(Dataiku),助力全球的模型开发团队将每个模型的开发周期从 6 个月缩短到 1~2 个月。项目获得通用电气数字业务集团 2019 年度数字表彰日刚毅奖(G. R. I. T. Award)提名。

教育背景

2010/9-2015/7 上海交通大学密西根学院——机械工程硕士1

2006/9-2010/7 上海交通大学密西根学院——机械工程学士,优秀毕业生

培训和证书

■ 阿里云 ACP 认证

■ PMP(完成培训)

■ CFA 通过一级考试

专业技能

■ 英语: 商务流利

■ MS Office: 熟悉

■ 机器学习:熟悉基于 sklearn 的经典机器学习算法,了解深度学习和强化学习的基本原理

■ Python: 精通

R: 熟悉

■ SQL: 熟练

¹因个人原因以硕士研究生学历和学位结束原计划5年的直博项目。